<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="http://www.the-star.co.ke/star-health" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Star-health </title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/star-health</link>
    <description></description>
    <language>en</language>
          <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-167389/delicate-surgery-gives-girl-life-and-chance-swim&quot;&gt;Delicate surgery gives girl life and chance to swim&lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/features%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EFeatures%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;For every 1,000 children born in Kenya, about eight of them come with heart defects. Anne Wangari says a million questions flashed through her mind when her three-month-old daughter was diagnosed with a “ hole” in the heart in 2009. There was also shock, disbelief and denial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; She found herself questioning the quality of life her daughter would lead. How would she cope as she grew up? Jasmine Nduta is now a bubbly, five-year-old pre-unit pupil at Ruiru&#039;s Viola Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; “She is always active and very playful but cannot stand for long. She easily contracts infections, so we cannot allow her in some games like swimming,” says Wangari, a teacher at Nairobi&#039;s Light Academy. “She often asks me, Mum, when will I start swimming. My answer has always been, soon, my dear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Medics first noted Jasmine had a problem in 2009 because she could not straighten up properly when being weighed, and she had low weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; She was treated but there were detectable murmurs from her heart. Wangari and her husband James Chege, an army officer, took her for more tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Hurlingham-based cardiologist Dr Celeste Okello finally carried out an echo and discovered Jasmine had a ventricular septal defect (VSD), commonly called a hole in the heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Some VSDs are not detected until a person reaches adulthood. Signs can include shortness of breath and a loud heart murmur when the doctor listens with a stethoscope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The defect involves a hole forming between the heart&#039;s lower chambers, allowing oxygen-rich and oxygen-poor blood to mix. If untreated, it can result in life-threatening complications like permanent damage to the lung arteries and pulmonary hypertension. Some extreme cases cause heart failure or stroke. Jasmine was finally wheeled to the theatre at Mater Hospital in Nairobi two weeks ago for a delicate operation to seal the hole. The two-hour open-heart surgery was led by the head of cardiology department at the University of Nairobi, Dr James Munene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operation cost more than Sh500,000 but was heavily subsidised by the Mater Heart Run, a charity programme that has since 1996 funded more than 2,500 heart treatments for children at the hospital. It is a delicate operation where the heart is put to rest and a bypass machine pumps blood around the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Dr Simon Nderitu, cardiac surgeon, first makes an incision in the chest to reach the heart. Dr Munene, who leads the operation, examines the defect and begins to prepare a special patch that will cover the 0.8cm hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Dr Munene says such holes are treatable. “The small holes actually close on their own or don&#039;t cause problems,” he says. He says many people with the small defects live normal, productive lives with few related problems.Those with larger holes, like Jasmine, require surgical repair early in life to prevent complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Dr Munene says its not known exactly why congenital heart defects like VSDs develop and mothers should not think they did something wrong during pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; He says while such operations carry some risk, those done at Mater have been highly successful because patients first undergo a litany of tests. Complications, such as bleeding and infection, from VSD surgery are rare, he says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; After two grueling hours, tests show the hole in Jasmine&#039;s heart has been successfully sealed. There is no leakage. The surgeons and the cardiac nurses begin sending blood back to the heart which, almost miraculously, begins kicking with vigour. Dr Munene slowly closes the chest after further tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Doctors expect her to lead a normal lifestyle. She can finally learn swimming without having to worry about swimming pool infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Jasmine hopes to participate in this year&#039;s Mater’s Heart Run next Saturday in Nairobi. Her parents have already bought the Sh1,000 t-shirt for her and more for other family members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; “She&#039;s back to her feet! She has one more scheduled clinic visit before resuming school. She can&#039;t wait to run next week, and finally learn how to swim!” her mother says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Mater head of marketing Lawrence Muiga said this year they are targeting Sh70 million to fund heart operations at least 300 children. “We usually evaluate the financial ability of parents or guardians and and come up with a cost-sharing plan,” he says. They have already screened 100 children, who will be operated on once money is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The annual charity run takes place on Saturday May 24 in Nairobi and other parts of Kenya. “Children contributors have always raised 70 per cent of the funds,” Muiga adds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; He says last year approximately 50,000 supporters turned out to run in three venues in Nairobi, Mombasa and Mumias. They raised Sh54 million, which funded 231 heart surgeries. “Jasmine is now fine. We&#039;ll all run to support other children like her,” says Wangari.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>05/16/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY JOHN MUCHANGI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-167389/delicate-surgery-gives-girl-life-and-chance-swim&quot;&gt;Delicate surgery gives girl life and chance to swim&lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-164849/womans-nightmares-end-after-30-year-struggle-fistula&quot;&gt;Woman&amp;#039;s nightmares end after 30-year struggle with fistula&lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/major%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EMajor%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;There exists a very thin line between the joy of motherhood and childbirth complications. Dressed in a pink gown, 65-year-old Joyce Mumbi sits on a bed at Guru Nanak Hospital in Nairobi awaiting her turn to go to the theatre. She has lived with fistula for more than 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mumbi had turned up for the free vesical vaginal fistula (VVF) camp organised recently by the Flying Doctors Society of Africa. More than 200 women benefitted from the corrective surgery at a cost of Sh10 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mumbi started having complications after getting her second child at the age of 16. After examination, doctors said her vagina is torn and that she has fistula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mumbi was brought to the hospital by well-wishers from All Saints CPK in Muchatha, Kiambu county, where she is a member. Nurses at the hospital said she came in traumatised and not ready for the operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have had to take her through counselling to have her agree to the treatment,” said Christine Muthengi, a nurse at the ward where Mumbi was admitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hers has been a painful journey. All her eight children were born prematurely and all ended up dying. “I was giving birth at home and none of my children survived. None of them reached full term — I was getting them between the sixth and the eight month,” she explained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She says she gave up after the eighth child died and accepted that her fate was to live without children. “I appreciate the support I get from my church members who decided to bring me here. Those are the people I look at as my children,” she says, adding that she never feels alone since she is still married.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She admits that through the years, she has been mocked by many in her village.  Sometimes people would move away from her in church and other public places because she at times stinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sometimes I have a foul-smelling discharg&lt;em&gt;e &lt;/em&gt;which makes &lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;me very uncomfortable,” says Mumbi, who is a small-scale farmer and a bananas seller at a market in Kiambu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doctors say some of the home births must have been difficult which resulted in the damage of the vagina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjacent to Mumbi sits another fistula victim, Emma Wambui, who is a mother of two. Wambui, who is in her twenties, has lived with fistula for two years. “It all happened after I got my second child. At first I thought the problem would disappear but it got worse with time,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She says she has been visiting various hospitals and was meant to undergo an operation which would have cost her almost Sh40,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She says she is happy that the camp is doing free fistula correction and thanks the organisers for coming to their rescue. “I have not paid a coin for the treatment,” said Wambui who had already had the operation done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She is hopeful that she will now be able to enjoy her life all over again. “I want the bad smell to go and to stop wetting my clothes. I want to regain respect and dignity from the community and stop walking around with extra clothes,” she said with a smile on her face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nairobi governor Evans Kidero&#039;s wife Susan Kidero, who launched the camp, called for an all-inclusive effort to free women from fistula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Poverty is one of the underlying causes as it is associated with early marriages, unwanted pregnancies, malnutrition and lack of access to medical care,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flying Doctors Society of Africa chairperson Eunice Kiereini expressed concern at rising cases of fistula and urged expectant women to seek medical attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are an estimated 3,000 new cases of fistula each year in the country and the main cause of the condition is obstructed labour,” she noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This condition is the most devastating of all pregnancy-related injuries affecting more than 100,000 African women each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Annually, there are 5,000 cases of fistula in each East African country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fistula mostly affects poor women and girls who cannot afford skilled supervised deliveries at a health facility. It is caused by difficult and prolonged labour, according to Dr Khisa Wakasiaka, a VVF specialist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This happens when a baby is too big and the birth canal is too small. When the mother instills pressure to push the baby, tissues such as urethra, bladder and vaginal walls get trapped between the bones,” he explained. He warns that the condition can only be treated through surgery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While obstructed labour is the highest cause of fistula at 92 per cent, there are other causes among them violent rape, abortion, radiation from pelvic radiotherapy, pelvic surgery, severe forms of female genital mutilation and sexually transmitted infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite fistula cases being very high, there are only eight fistula surgeons in Kenya.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that fistula leads to up to eight per cent of maternal deaths worldwide. The situation is worse among teenagers and first-time mothers due to under-developed pelvises. Fistula does not only subject the victim to physical harm, it significantly denies her dignity thereby contributing to families and marriages disintegrating and stigmatisation of the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>04/28/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY MONICAH MWANGI                                                                                                                                                                                    </dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-164849/womans-nightmares-end-after-30-year-struggle-fistula&quot;&gt;Woman&amp;#039;s nightmares end after 30-year struggle with fistula&lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-164064/tropical-medicine-research-institute-targets-neglected-deadly-diseases&quot;&gt;Tropical Medicine Research Institute Targets Neglected Deadly Diseases &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/major%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EMajor%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Antwerp institute builds knowledge on tropical diseases and public health issues &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Our vision is of a world in which aid is finite, but scientific collaboration isn’t.” &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe Muga, Weekend Editor of The Star, and Roeland Scholtalbers (Head of Communications – Institute of Tropical Medicine in Antwerp) met at the World Conference of Science Journalists held in Helsinki, in 2013. The following is the transcript of a subsequent conversation on the work of the ITM:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: Tell me a little about the history, background and founding of the Institute of Tropical Medicine, Antwerp?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: It was founded in 1906 in Brussels as the School of Tropical diseases. In 1934, it moved to Antwerp, where we are still based and it became the Institute of Tropical Medicine. Why? Because ships to the Congo colony left from the docks of Antwerp’s port.The Belgians were very much involved in public health in their colony, Congo. In those days, the institute trained people who were going to the tropics, while it also served as a hospital for those returning ill. However, after decolonization in 1960, ITM became a specialized part of the Belgian system of higher education. At that point, it no longer trained colonials, but experts in development cooperation. During this period our contacts with the developing world intensified and staff started to travel to developing countries to teach and train people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our educational portfolio grew; we also started working on animal health, for example. At the end of the 1960s, we added a Master in Public Healthto our curriculum and we gradually acquired a more international student population. In the 1970s our research component expanded greatly. We started setting up research lines in developing countries; medical care, cooperation with scientists, institutes and local authorities. We no longer merely focused on treating diseases as we moved to epidemiology, organization of health systems and those kinds of elements. This was based on the fact that diseases not only have a biological side, but socio-economical determinants as well. That is how our institute developed from the early period of colonialism through the ’60s and ’70s to the three components we have today; education, research and medical services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: That&#039;s a very rich history indeed. But I&#039;m sure, in the one hundred and ten years, you must have had some great achievements and some disappointments as everything couldn&#039;t have gone your way. Could you tell us about them?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: Of course. It would be hard though, and probably unfair, to mention just one achievement for such a multifaceted institute. But there are things that set us apart from other organizations, like our focus on neglected diseases affecting the poorest, or our role as HIV pioneers. For example, fighting sleeping sickness would not have been possible without diagnostics developed at ITM, whilst since the early days we have contributed to research on the HIV virus and care for HIV/AIDS patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: How did your institute’s work on HIV develop?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: We were in the first line when this new, unknown virus caused a great scare throughout the world at the beginning of the 1980s. Peter Piot, the former director of UNAIDS and current director of the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, was a young researcher at ITM when the disease broke out. He, and several colleagues still working at the institute today, were closely involved in the discovery of what HIV actually was and how it spread, in Africa. They set up research lines and provided care to the first patients. That was a very intense period, which laid the foundations for our HIV work today. The HIV virus is a difficult virus; we have learned so much about it, yet it is still impossible to develop a vaccine or a cure. But our laboratory, clinical and epidemiological research have provided several important insights which have contributed to turn a deadly disease into a chronic one, as long as people stay on antiretroviral treatment. We closely follow-up many HIV patients and we are also a national reference centre for HIV. We also look for ways to make it quicker and easier to perform an HIV test, for example through a swab test which looks for antibodies against HIV in the saliva. Our HIV expertise is multidisciplinary, which is one of our strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: You mentioned your expertise on neglected diseases; could you tell us what they are?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: We are proud to be at the forefront against diseases like Leishmaniasis, Buruli ulcer, bilharzia and sleeping sickness that few people work on and even less people talk about. Neglected diseases affect millions of poor people worldwide, yet very few medicines or vaccines are being developed for these diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take Human African Trypanosomiasis, or sleeping sickness, which is caused by the trypanosome parasite transmitted by the bite of a tsetse fly.This parasite then multiplies in the blood and evades the human immune system and settles in our organs; heart, kidneys. It weakens patients, it messes up their sleep patterns – hence the name sleeping sickness – and it causes motor and mental problems. If left untreated, this leads to coma and death. WHO estimates that it claims between 10,000 and 20,000 lives each year, mainly in Central Africa. Most cases occur in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. Now you might say there is a large gap between 10,000 and 20,000 lives. That is because there is a lot of uncertainty, because most cases go undetected. The people who get the disease live in remote villages with little access to healthcare, one of the main problems of sleeping sickness. The progress made so far in reducing the number of new cases wouldn’t have been possible without the diagnostic tools that were and are still developed at ITM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: How does that work, diagnosing sleeping sickness?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: For nearly thirty years mobile teams have used our CATT test, an agglutination test, to screen a lot of people in a short time. Last year, our researchers co-developed individual rapid tests which allow medics to get a diagnosis within 15 minutes and that does not require to be stored in a fridge. This is important, because if diagnosed in time this disease is easy to treat, but once the brain is invaded it becomes more and more difficult to treat, with some of the medicines required having deadly side effects. The rapid tests are easily administered and every health worker with a bit of instructions and training can perform this test. The rapid tests are produced by companies, but they all contain our antigens used to detect the parasite causing the disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: Just to get an idea of how widespread this disease is, you have mentioned 10,000-20,000 deaths. Do you have any estimate of those infected yet survive; or incidence rate?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: Tens of millions of people are at risk of sleeping sickness across more than 25 countries in Sub- Saharan Africa. In 2009, the number of reported cases for the first time dropped just below 10.000 as a result of the control efforts. The incidence rate is thus low. As mentioned earlier though, many cases go undetected. If diagnosed early treatment is rather straightforward, but the disease is deadly if left untreated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: DRC is a very poor country in a state of semi-civil war most of the time. Unless someone from outside came to perform this research, I doubt there is capacity within DRC to carry out the research. I would say definitely that is a great achievement, especially since it&#039;s not prompted by monetary considerations but by the mission of the institute.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: Let me pick on that as that&#039;s where the story gets more interesting, because things are changing.Today, we are in a situation where the prevalence of sleeping sickness is decreasing and the strategy of going out to the field with mobile teams is proving less and less effective. Screening for sleeping sickness should be integrated in the normal health system. That might not sound too exciting but it is a very important thing to do. Now, the DRC is trying to make this work. On the one hand, we are supporting the operational activities of the national sleeping sickness programme. On the other, we carry out several research projects on diagnostic tools, as well as screening and treatment strategies in close collaboration with the national reference laboratory for sleeping sickness in Kinshasa. I should stress here that this means that the DRC is in the driving seat and we enter into play when our specific expertise is required. This neatly fits in our vision of a world in which aid is finite, but scientific collaboration isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: The institute has indeed done some pioneering work. But going forward, say 50 or 100 years to come, where will your focus be? Will it still be a focus on the neglected diseases in low income countries or will it be on global challenges such as HIV? What is the vision of the organization?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: You know what, this question gives me a good entry point to also mention one of our shortcomings, or disappointments you asked about earlier. As an institute, we should perhaps have explicated our vision of “beyond aid” earlier. You might be familiar with this concept aboutgoing beyond the paternalistic concept of northern-driven development aid. That is a formula which has its roots in the past, you could say the colonial past. But it is something we are trying to change, as in the example I mentioned in the DRC. If you look at our mission in the 1970s, it was to strengthen healthcare in developing countries and it very much read like we were the ones who were going to do that. Then in 1995, it had become strengthening the rationale of healthcare in developing countries and thus helping these countries build up basic healthcare, scientific capacity and we are definitely very much in the process. I will tell you more about that journey, which we call ‘Switching the Poles’, later. But for 2020 and beyond, we actually want to move to a role where we stimulate scientific research on tropical and poverty-related diseases, whilst developing countries are increasingly able to run their own business. That might sound a little bit like a slogan but it&#039;s really something that we believe in and we put a lot of effort in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: Why is it so important to move to a different type of cooperation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: This is about countries and people taking charge of their own future.Tropical and poverty-related diseases, such as tuberculosis, have the greatest impact in low- and middle-income countries. It does make sense to treat them and deal with them as close as possible as to where they happen. Through an extensive programme funded by Belgian Development Cooperation, we are strengthening the capacity of long-term partners across Africa, Asia and Latin America to enable them to do research, to care for patients, to train professionals and take up a pivotal role in their health system. Maybe an anecdote or an example is in place: This is something I have seen with my own eyes just a few months ago in Cotonou, Benin, at the Laboratoire de Référence de Mycobactériologie (LRM). LRM specializes in diseases caused by mycobacteria like tuberculosis or Buruli ulcer, which is a disease causing mutilating scars which are very difficult to treat. For years, like other laboratories in Africa and around the world, they have been sending samples to ITM to get them analyzed and receive results from ITM. But we get many, if not too many, requests and it is not really efficient to continue doing that in Antwerp. We will increasingly focus on quality checks of other institutes, which take over some of our tasks. LRM has been very good in doing so. A former PhD student at ITM, who has learned a lot of the important knowledge on Buruli ulcer, TB and laboratory techniques in Antwerp, heads up the lab at LRM. The laboratory is now a candidate to become a WHO supranational reference centre for West Africa for these two diseases. That means that other West African countries come to LRM to get their samples analyzed. I think it is a beautiful example of an African country or institute taking ownership of a very important issue. Every day at LRM you have nearly 100 patients who come with suspected TB. They have an excellent laboratory to make the right diagnosis and for further monitoring during treatment. We are talking about microscopy, sputum culture and modern techniques such as PCR (Polymerase Chain Reaction), including molecular fingerprinting. They perform analyses at the same standard as we do in Antwerp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: That&#039;s the future as you see it. If I understood you correctly, you are talking of establishing partnerships globally but specifically in the areas where certain diseases are prevalent or widely found so that the research can be done and owned there as opposed to in the North. Furthermore local capacity can be built to do the same standard of scientific research and medical care you are doing at ITM. Is that more or less it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: That&#039;s correct. The example I gave regarded laboratory work, but the same applies for supporting partners who specialize in medical studies or in action research in communities. Also here applies that we share our expertise across disciplines. But I would add that from Antwerp we will continue to contribute to build knowledge on tropical diseases and public health issues. This is because they are issues of global relevance due to the interconnected world we live in, think trade, tourism,migration. Climate change is another factor playing a role. These issues affect us all, whether we are in Antwerp or Nairobi. Our role is changing, but we will still have a role to play in these issues which are truly global.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: Within all this, if it&#039;s not an unfair question to ask, who funds you? Where does the money come from to support all this work? Is it the Government of Belgium? Is it international organizations?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: Indeed our core funding comes from the Belgian Government. We also get funding from the European Commission and we get increasingly private donations for cutting-edge research projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: Is there any private foundation you could mention in particular or you are not beneficiaries of funds from, for example, the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: Absolutely. Just to give you an example, the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation funds some of our work on malaria in Asia, where we try to see what the impact is of the mass use of mosquito repellents. But it is the public support that enables us to perform our core activities (education, research and medical services) at the highest standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: Thank you. To conclude, I would like to touch on some of the diseases which are very much in global headlines or what you might say are appealing from the international general community point of view. You have told us of your work on AIDS, malaria. Do you have anything to mention on TB and polio?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: We do not have research lines on polio, but our expertise on TB is acknowledged internationally. Antibiotic resistance is on the rise globally, and multi-drug resistant TB is a big issue. With only a few new antibiotics in the making, it is legitimate to wonder whether we might head towards a future without effective drugs. Resistance to the medicines is induced by things like incorrect use, but also because pathogens are very smart and continue to evolve. Now, having enough strains of different types of resistant TB is of the essence to be able to develop new diagnostic and new medicines. We actually have the largest collection of TB strains which is available to the research community, smaller organizations with little funds, as well as private and larger companies, to test new diagnostics and medicines. I think that is something to be proud of. That being said there are also things being done in the field. For example, ITM researcher Armand Van Deun, in collaboration with the Damien Foundation, came up with a new cocktail of medicines to shorten the treatment of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis from 18-24 months to only 9 months. The success rate of treatment increased from 65% to 88%.Resistant tuberculosis is a global problem and it requires new solutions. It is rather scary that very little is moving on antibiotic resistance, whilst on other diseases, like HIV, progress is being made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: One last question, just give us an idea of the size of the institution? How many people work there? Could you tell us in what categories?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: We have at the moment 470 staff members working at ITM. Yearly 500 students – medical doctors, biologists, veterinarians, but also social scientists – from all over the world join us to specialize in tropical medicine and public health. More than 100 PhD students are currently working on their doctoral theses at ITM. Another interesting fact for you to know is that we provide around 35,000 vaccinations to travelers going to tropical areas. Our doctors also provide care for HIV patients. We host 13 national and international reference laboratories on a range of diseases. This gives you an idea of the scope of our institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: That is a very large institution. Would you also say it&#039;s one of the best in the world?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roeland: I think it definitely is. It is unique in its kind in the sense that our expertise continues to build up thanks to our research, clinical activities and field experiences. That knowledge is being shared and put to good use. We pass on skills to nurses, doctors, social scientists, biomedical scientists, a variety of health professionals, who go on and really make the difference wherever it is in the world. Hence, it&#039;s fair to say that if you have passed through ITM, you hold all the cards to play a significant role in tackling tropical and poverty-related diseases. We have plenty of prominent alumni. Just to give you an example; Dr. Nafsiah Mboi, Minister of Health in Indonesia and current chair of the Global Fund, studied at the Institute of Tropical Medicine. There are many who, like her, have made a difference and that definitely makes us proud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wycliffe: Thank you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>04/21/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY WYCLIFFE MUGA</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-164064/tropical-medicine-research-institute-targets-neglected-deadly-diseases&quot;&gt;Tropical Medicine Research Institute Targets Neglected Deadly Diseases &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158904/fight-against-hiv-pre-exposure-prophylaxis&quot;&gt;Fight Against HIV- Pre - Exposure Prophylaxis &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/features%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EFeatures%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time back, the international media was flooded with reports of a baby in Mississippi who was cured of HIV. The miraculous procedure was performed by Dr. Gray, a pediatrician with the University of Massachusetts alongside Dr. Persaud of John Hopkins University. The daring move to treat the child before confirmatory test results of infection was done thirty hours after the child’s birth. In addition, Dr. Gray went a step further to use three drugs instead of the usual one or two. This could have posed a health risk, but against all odds the child survived and eighteen months later, was found to have no viral load despite the mother having discontinued the antiretroviral therapy. The one question on everyone’s mind was: Could this be the breakthrough in finding the cure to HIV/AIDS epidemic? We would all like to think so, but the fact still remains that there are over 34 Million people living with HIV globally and 1.7 Million fatalities annually. In Kenya, there are 1.6 Million people living with HIV and with such figures, the main focus currently is not to find a cure but to prevent transmission of HIV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several trials have been launched over the past few years to investigate whether certain drugs could be used to curb HIV infection before exposure. One such study funded by the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation was started in Kenya in 2011. The Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis (PrEP) study showed reduced risk of HIV acquisition by 73%. Another trial known as VOICE (Vaginal and Oral Intervention to Control the Epidemic) whose results were released on 4th March 2013 proved that the battle was far from over. The results indicated that none of the three pre-exposure prophylaxis and microbicide intervention provided additional protection against HIV in the study. The large scale trial among African women utilized daily oral tenofovir, daily oral Truvada (TDF/FTC) and daily 1% vaginal tenofovir gel. However, the disappointing results were not due to the inefficiency of the drugs themselves, but were more likely as a result of the large number of women who did not use the products as directed. The results which were presented in Atlanta at the 20th Conference on Retroviruses and Opportunistic Infections (CROI) confirmed the correlation between higher levels of adherence and protection from HIV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The VOICE results reinforce what we already know from previous trials: these interventions work when they are used, and they don’t work when they are not used,” said Mitchell Warren, AVAC (AIDS Vaccine Advocacy Coalition) Executive Director. “PrEP is still a valuable option for many women, and men, who recognize their risk and can take PrEP consistently. Now we have a dual responsibility to understand who might benefit from daily PrEP and ensure that they can access it, and to accelerate the development of additional options that can meet the urgent needs of others.” In simpler terms, for the drugs to work they have to be taken as indicated. As this is a matter of life and death, we cannot afford to treat it in the same manner that most of us do a prescribed dose of antibiotics. We simply cannot take the drugs for two days and once the cough ‘disappears’, we forget the other pills and assume that we are ‘healed’. For the VOICE and other trial medications, it is paramount that the patients take the full dose as HIV will not just ‘disappear’. This raises an important question: What can be done to encourage people to take the drugs as directed or even to take the medication in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The women of VOICE and other prevention trials have much to tell us. Now we need to listen to what they are saying and design prevention options based on a better understanding of their reproductive and sexual health needs and desires, their perceptions of personal risk for HIV infection, and their interest in and ability to use the products offered in those trials,” Warren said. In Partners of PrEP study performed in Kenya, some people cited the ‘pill burden’ to be one of the reasons for lack of adherence. Others were afraid of the stigma associated with HIV and therefore to avoid people thinking that they were infected yet they were not, they would not the drugs or at least not every day. This would defeat the whole purpose of the drugs which is to prevent transmission before one is exposed to the virus. Therefore there is need to package the drugs in such a way that the recipients will comfortably use it, hence promote adherence and in doing so will decrease the rate of HIV transmission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, AVAC called for accelerated research and development of additional HIV prevention options that rely less on adherence making it easier and more desirable for use. For example, different delivery mechanisms such as long-acting rings and injection and less stringent dosing schedules as is with FACTS 001 trial which is looking at 1% tenofovir vaginal gel used around the time of sex. The call by AVAC is echoed the world over stemming from the WHO report showing that there are over 2.5 Million new HIV infection annually with 330, 000 being children under the age of fifteen. The high incidence rate was also reflected in the VOICE trial results. Elizabeth Bukusi, Deputy Director (Research and Training) of the Kenya Medical Research Institute (KEMRI) and an AVAC board member had this to say, “The high rates of new HIV infections among women, especially young women, are the most shocking and disturbing data from this trial. They are a sobering reminder of how desperately women need new prevention options that they can and will use to protect themselves from HIV.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis was the message of the year 2013, but in Kenya where over 600,000 people are on antiretrovirals in Kenya, a large coverage gap of approximately 30% still remains. We are yet to effectively broadcast the message that is anti-retroviral therapy. Which raises the question, what is our message for the year 2014?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>03/15/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY DIANA WANGARI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158904/fight-against-hiv-pre-exposure-prophylaxis&quot;&gt;Fight Against HIV- Pre - Exposure Prophylaxis &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158905/can-pill-day-prevent-hiv&quot;&gt;Can a pill a day prevent HIV?&lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/features%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EFeatures%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;!--    @page { margin: 0.79in }    P { margin-bottom: 0.08in }  --&gt;&lt;p&gt; A study was done to test whether taking a pill daily before exposure to HIV would reduce HIV transmission. The drugs used were oral Tenofovir and Truvada. As it was to prevent (prophylaxis) transmission BEFORE one was exposed to HIV it was named Pre-Exposure prophylaxis (PrEP). In simpler terms, the study used two drugs to find out if there is a decrease in HIV transmission in circumstance where one partner is positive and the other is not. The HIV negative partner was enrolled in the study and placed under one of the two drugs with some being given a placebo, though they were later reassigned to the active drug. There was a reduction of HIV transmission of 63% on Tenofovir and 75% on Truvada in comparison to the placebo. Now before we all break out in song and dance to rejoice that finally there might be a way of preventing transmission of HIV, we ought to consider one thing, ADHERENCE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many people will take a pill daily continuously? How many of us complete a dose of antibiotics in the first place? If a pill is released into the market that can prevent HIV, people are bound to take the pill only when they are about to indulge in unprotected sex. Worse still, they might use it only with partners who ‘appear to be sick’. “He can’t have HIV look how big he is. If he was positive, he would be skin and bones,” these were the comments of Anne during a presentation by an HIV positive patient. Sad but true, some people remain trapped in the still backwaters of long defunct ideas whereby they think you can tell whether a person is infected or not by their appearance. Therefore the challenge might not be the discovery of such drugs, but its use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A comparison of whether people would take the drug as indicated was done in Kisumu. 95% of the participants claimed to have taken the drug daily as recommended, but after testing the drug levels in their blood only 85% were proven to have told the truth. Dr. Beatrice Wamuti of the Kenya Medical Research Institute who took part in the adherence study had this to say, “Despite having implemented social science, where we ensured that the community was educated about the study and the potential effect on reducing HIV transmission, some participant still lied about taking the drug daily.” She went on to site that side effects of the medication, which included nausea and vomiting, as one of the reasons for patients not taking the drugs as required. However stigma and lack of motivation were key factors. “Some participants did not want other people to see them taking the study medication. They said that other people would accuse them of being HIV positive (remember the drugs were given to the partner who was HIV negative partner to reduce chances of transmission),” she adds, shaking her head with disappointment of the impact of criticism on health matters. It got to a point that some participants dropped out of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abuse is a key concern if these drugs are successful. If PrEP is approved, people will be tempted to not use condoms and generally to be more careless in terms of HIV prevention strategies. In addition, many will opt for intermittent use of PrEP while the study focused on mandatory once-a-day intake. This may have a negative effect by increasing resistance to the medication in case one gets HIV infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to PrEP, that is using drugs to prevent HIV before being exposed to HIV, we cannot rejoice as yet. A lot of policy issues will need to be resolved for example, where will PrEP be dispensed, will people be able to buy them over the counter, will the government be able to foot the bill for PrEP? But more importantly, will the people adhere to the recommendations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>03/15/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY DIANA WANGARI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158905/can-pill-day-prevent-hiv&quot;&gt;Can a pill a day prevent HIV?&lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158907/multi-drug-resistant-tb-still-menace&quot;&gt;Multi Drug Resistant TB Still a Menace &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/features%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EFeatures%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Tuberculosis is ranked second among the infectious agents with highest mortality rates. According the WHO, 8.7 million people were infected with TB in 2011 with 1.4million deaths. This can be translated to approximately 1,500 deaths every day where 10% of these are children. Despite the high incidence rate, there appeared to be a silver lining after investigations showed a decrease in new infections and an estimated 85% success rate in treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there was the emergence of multi-drug resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) and the same drugs that were once effective became worthless against this strain of tuberculosis. MDR-TB is caused by organisms that are resistant to the first line anti-TB drugs, both isoniazid and rifampicin. This reduced the number of drugs that can safely treat patients with this strain of TB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mismanagement of TB treatment is the primary cause of resistance. For tuberculosis treatment, a strict six month drug regimen is provided to patients with support and supervision to ensure adherence. However, with lack of adherence and ineffective formulations being circulated, resistance developed. New strains that proved too clever for the two most powerful first line drugs emerged. And once again, incidence of tuberculosis infection began to rise.  In Kenya, 2300 patients were reported to have MDR-TB. Globally, 3.7% of new TB infections were multi-drug resistant whereas 20% relapsed with the new strain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of MDR-TB is so insidious that the stop TB Partnership Goal Plan estimates that there will be one million MDR-TB patients between 2011 and 2015 who will be diagnosed and placed on treatment. What happens to the undetected cases? They will probably continue to transmit the infection as a person only needs to inhale a few of these organisms to become infected. In fact, about one third of the world’s population has latent TB which means they have been infected with TB but aren’t (at least not yet) ill with the disease. The good news is that if you do not have the disease, you cannot transmit the infection.  In as much as Kenya was ranked 13th in the list of high TB burden countries worldwide, we have doubled our efforts in the fight against the TB epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was evidenced by the launch of the KEMRI/CDC lab in Nyanza which was the first lab to undertake TB culture testing apart from the Central Reference lab based in Nairobi. The decentralization was a much needed change as Dr. Joseph Sitienei, Director of the National Leprosy and TB control Programme (NLTP) explained, “The emergence of multi drug resistant TB is posing a great threat to TB treatment especially in Nyanza where TB cases are on the increase.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He went on to reveal that Kenya is the first country in East and Central Africa to detect Extensively Drug Resistant TB (XDR-TB). Thus, a new concept is introduced. XDR-TB is a form of TB caused by organisms that are resistant to isoniazid and rifampicin as well as any fluoroquinolone and any of the second line injectable anti-TB drugs. Yes, just as we were beginning to combat MDR-TB, the strain of XDR-TB emerges with a 9% worldwide incidence rate. In addition, 4 new cases of a Totally Drug Resistant TB (TDR-TB) have been reported in India, though it is yet to be clearly described.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, these forms of TB do not respond to the standard TB treatment course and can take up to three years to treat with more toxic, more expensive and less potent drugs. As far as TB treatment goes, appropriate use and international standards must be maintained as the infection could outsmart us.  Diana Wangari&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>03/15/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY DIANA WANGARI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158907/multi-drug-resistant-tb-still-menace&quot;&gt;Multi Drug Resistant TB Still a Menace &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158899/letter-mombasa-where-there-no-doctor&quot;&gt;Letter From Mombasa: Where There Is No Doctor &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/opinion%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EOpinion%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;!--  P { margin-bottom: 0.08in; direction: ltr; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); }P.western { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.cjk { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.ctl { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }  --&gt;&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, a documentary on a local TV channel featured an interview with a traditional herbalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not a wild-eyed man draped in the ‘traditional’ animal skins. He wore a suit, and was speaking excellent English as he showed the journalist around the garden behind his clinic, pausing here and there to give a brief account of the medicinal powers of the many plants he had growing there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His explanations went something like this: &quot;This one here is very good for chest pains – that one cures stomach trouble of every kind – that is good for joint pains in old men.” And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing something of the work of herbalists in Kenya, I was not really paying much attention, until I heard a claim that had me sitting up in amazement. This was when, without altering his tone or raising his voice, or in any way suggesting that what he was just about to say was of major significance, he went on to announce as he paused over a small shrub, “This one cures cancer.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impression given by his casual mention of this infallible cure for cancer was that he was merely affirming a well-known fact. And that it was no more likely that his claim over the properties of the cancer-curing plant would be doubted, than that his prescription for joint pains would be criticised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this sort of thing that creates an impression that all this talk of herbal or traditional medicine in many African countries is little more than an elaborate scam for exploiting the ignorance of poor and superstitious people. And these practitioners of traditional herbal medicine don’t do themselves any favour either by invariably giving themselves titles like ‘professor’ or ‘doctor’ when advertising their services in the media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more famous ones move from town to town, dispensing their herbal cures in large bottles. Prominent among these a decade or so ago, was one ‘professor’ who had allegedly created his own unique “chameleon wonder drug” which was said to somehow camouflage itself as it moved within the bloodstream, hunting down and destroying the AIDS virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great pity in all this is that such traditional herbalists are not a rare and exotic breed in Kenya, but are to be found in virtually every village in the countryside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And official figures from the Ministry of Planning of a few years back, indicated that no less than 70 per cent of Kenya&#039;s population relies on traditional medicine – a clear sign that most Kenyans still seek out the local herbalist when they fall ill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a well-known book titled, &lt;em&gt;Where there is no doctor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a self-help guide to treating medical problems likely to be faced at the village level by poor and isolated communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have seen this book in many Kenyan bookshops, but not once have I seen it in a village school, or in the homes of any poor Kenyans living in the rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would seem that the sort of people for whom this book was intended, do not feel that they need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They already have, after all, their village herbalists, who cannot only treat burns, diarrhea or chest pains, but can also – apparently – cure cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>03/15/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY WYCLIFFE MUGA</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158899/letter-mombasa-where-there-no-doctor&quot;&gt;Letter From Mombasa: Where There Is No Doctor &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158901/letter-boston-africas-greatest-health-crisis&quot;&gt;Letter From Boston: Africas Greatest Health Crisis &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/opinion%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EOpinion%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;!--  P { margin-bottom: 0.08in; direction: ltr; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); }P.western { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.cjk { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.ctl { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }  --&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the US, for many years all the presidential candidates were asked to outline a detailed plan for providing universal healthcare. President Obama has at last managed to pull this off – but even then his programme (generally referred to as ‘Obamacare’) has its many loud and unrelenting critics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In France, the president is grappling with the need to reform the French state-run health system, which already provides universal coverage – this being part of a larger effort to review the lavish entitlements of this advanced welfare state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in Africa, on every single day, ten 747 jetliners filled with frightened children crash and kill all on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may well ask, “But how is it that news of these crashing jets never makes it to the outside world? And what has this got to do with the healthcare systems of France and the US??”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, of course there has been no such daily aviation tragedy in Africa. But that does not mean that there is no tragedy of that magnitude occurring in Africa every single day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ten 747s filled with frightened children, is the image used by those campaigning to end the endemic malaria in Africa, to make a point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the point is that if ten large aircrafts filled with African children did indeed crash and kill all on board, African governments would be held accountable by the rest of the world for this horror, and Western nations would rush in to offer their help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But deaths caused by malaria do not occur in a dramatic and photogenic manner. They mostly take place in scattered and remote villages all over rural Africa. So no great attention is paid to them, even though malaria has long been recognised as Africa’s greatest health crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why has malaria not been given the same focused attention as has HIV/AIDS??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the view of Prof Dyann Wirth, the Director of the Harvard Malaria Initiative at the Harvard School of Public Health, there are two principal reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, AIDS is a relatively new health risk, and also affects people all over the world. And this has led to a huge global effort to find ways to fight it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, AIDS poses the threat of wiping out the productive workforce of many African countries, sparing only the very old or the very young.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This generated a sense of urgency, which has been lacking in the fight against malaria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For malaria is largely confined to the tropics, and mostly affects children under 5 years of age, and pregnant women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this I would extrapolate that the real reason that malaria programmes have not been effective, has to do with the self-interest of decision makers in Africa:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that African leaders felt personally threatened by AIDS, and so they put a great deal of effort into seeking help from outside to fight it. But they do not feel at all threatened by malaria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>03/15/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY WYCLIFFE MUGA</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158901/letter-boston-africas-greatest-health-crisis&quot;&gt;Letter From Boston: Africas Greatest Health Crisis &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158903/letter-boston-why-vaccination-failed-nigeria&quot;&gt;Letter From Boston: Why Vaccination Failed In Nigeria &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/opinion%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EOpinion%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;!--  P { margin-bottom: 0.08in; direction: ltr; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); widows: 2; orphans: 2; }P.western { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.cjk { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.ctl { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }  --&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before I had the opportunity to travel widely in Europe and the US, I shared the view held by many in Africa; that a disease like Avian Flu was a remote and exotic illness that did not concern me directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since then, having attended many conferences and seminars on ‘global health challenges’, it has become clear to me that the days are long gone, when the only illnesses you had to worry about were those which affected you and your neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This emphasis on taking a global approach to health arises from a recognition that diseases can travel very rapidly across borders. And that infectious illness in some remote corner of the developing world must be a matter of serious concern to health policy professionals everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is an increasing awareness that in some parts of the world, there are all sorts of social and political factors which matter almost as much as the availability of vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience of the fight against polio reveals how some of these factors work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although polio is incurable, and its crippling effects cannot be reversed, it can easily be prevented by a vaccine that has been available for the past 50 years. And a few years ago, only four countries were considered to still have endemic polio - Nigeria, India, Pakistan and Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of these, Nigeria had by far the largest number of polio cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And matters in Nigeria were then made worse when a polio vaccination campaign sponsored by the United Nations ran into a problem. Following rumours that these vaccines would eventually cause infertility, some of the influential traditional rulers in Northern Nigeria effectively blocked the programme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why was it that these allegations were able to frustrate this crucial public health intervention? Well, as was explained to me by a Nigerian friend, this has to do with both political and economic factors, unique to that country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Most of the Nigerian government’s budget is financed by oil revenues, and this oil is found only in the South of the country; and so Northern Nigeria is economically dependent on the South.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when it comes to national elections, it is the North that has the greater voting population. And this Northern vote is often the deciding factor in Nigerian presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaders in Northern Nigeria are as such well aware that anything that threatens to reduce the numbers of their followers will in the end diminish their ability to determine who gets to be president of Nigeria. And it is only by their influence in national elections, that they can ensure that government subsidies will continue to flow towards the North of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what makes such leaders susceptible to any rumours about medical interventions, which may somehow have a concealed birth control agenda behind them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the tragedy in all this is that the continued existence of polio in Northern Nigeria is not only a threat to the children of that country, but is a threat to children everywhere in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>03/15/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY WYCLIFFE MUGA</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158903/letter-boston-why-vaccination-failed-nigeria&quot;&gt;Letter From Boston: Why Vaccination Failed In Nigeria &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158912/not-about-poverty-aids-botswana&quot;&gt;Not About Poverty: Aids In Botswana &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/opinion%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EOpinion%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;!--  P { margin-bottom: 0.08in; direction: ltr; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); }P.western { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.cjk { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }P.ctl { font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;,serif; font-size: 12pt; }  --&gt;&lt;p&gt;All over Africa, there are people who believe that AIDS is caused by poverty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some say that this point of view has been reinforced by the leadership of South Africa, which had for long based its public health policies on a conviction that AIDS can be cured without anti-retroviral therapy. But there is actually more than that to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poor people tend to blame every misfortune that befalls them, on their poverty. They insist that it is only because they are poor that they have to face disappointment or suffering, and that the rich never have to endure such things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And no matter how much evidence may be presented to them to show that the rich also get to share in the misery and humiliation of this world, they will simply not believe it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue that something very similar applies to many nations in sub-Saharan Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For if the people of these countries were willing to consider the facts, they would not have to look very far for proof that there is no direct causal link between poverty in Africa and the prevalence of AIDS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example I have in mind is that of Botswana, a country which is the envy of many African nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Botswana is NOT a low-income country like most others in sub-Saharan Africa. It is classified by the World Bank as a middle-income country, which essentially means that its citizens have better access to clean water, health services and schools, and it also has better roads, telecommunications, and other public infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all this has come about in just 30 years. At its independence in 1966, Botswana was one of the poorest countries in the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how was this miracle achieved? Well, there are three basic reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, Botswana has been blessed with enlightened leadership and has never been held back by the kind of official corruption that other African countries have had to contend with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it was further blessed by having plenty of diamonds beneath its soils, which has given the country a huge financial windfall without which no such economic miracle would have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of its official websites, the Botswana government confirms that the country is the world’s most diamond-dependant economy, and that diamonds account for 50% of all revenues flowing into the national Treasury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it has a very small population to share in this wealth: just a little less than 2.0 million citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; But despite this prosperity, Botswana has the second highest HIV infection rate in the world. Although now estimated at &lt;span&gt;24%&lt;/span&gt; of all adults, in the year 2000, that number was by some accounts as high as 40%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cannot be explained in terms of poverty. The real reasons must involve the interaction of a variety of factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the tragic example of Botswana illustrates clearly that the conviction in many parts of Africa, that it is poverty that causes AIDS, is little more than superstition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>03/15/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY WYCLIFFE MUGA</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-158912/not-about-poverty-aids-botswana&quot;&gt;Not About Poverty: Aids In Botswana &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-156566/form-4-girl-hospital-after-failed-abortion&quot;&gt;Form 4 girl in hospital after failed abortion&lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/news%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3ENews%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;A form four student has been admitted to Rapcom Hospital in Awendo district after a failed abortion. The teenager had tried to procure an abortion at a chemist in Awendo town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the hospital on Saturday, the girl said her boyfriend who is a fellow student, first took her to Dede Dispensary but the medics declined to offer the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“After they refused, he gave me Sh4,500 to look for another clinic and left me alone,” she said. The girl said she went to Dan Chemist and Agrovet in Awendo town where an unsuccessful abortion was undertaken. “A medic called Dan inserted a metal and razor in my body and twisted them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bled and felt unbearable pain,” she said. She said she later went home before her elder sister noticed her condition the next day and took her to the hospital. Rapcom assistant administrator Joseph Otieno said cases of failed abortion are reported weekly at the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He urged parents to offer moral guidance to their children. “Most quacks in Awendo try to help girls abort and once they fail they often refer the case to us,” Otieno said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Dan Chemist and Agrovet proprietor Duncan Odhiambo denied the allegations. He was arrested and released on a Sh20,000 police bond.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>02/24/2014 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>By MANUEL ODENY</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-156566/form-4-girl-hospital-after-failed-abortion&quot;&gt;Form 4 girl in hospital after failed abortion&lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-147725/rape-and-elusive-p3-form&quot;&gt;Rape And The Elusive P3 Form&lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/major%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EMajor%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Obtaining the Kenya Police Medical Examination form or Police Form 3 (P3), as it is popularly known, should be one of the simplest procedures of government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The P3 is a legal document produced in court in cases of assault or rape. It is filled by a police officer and, later, a registered government doctor or clinical officer who examines the complainant to determine the cause and extent of his or her injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be widely accessible at every police station in the country and free of charge. Yet for three-year-old Baby Jane (not her real name) it took almost one month and a clever lie just to get one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Momanyi is one of just over 800 people who have been working fervently to ensure that the baby finds justice after she was defiled in July this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of Team Baby Jane began with a post on Soko Kuu, a Facebook business community by one of its members who asked not to be named in the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Hey wanasoko! A neighbour of mine hosting a child that she claims was abandoned at her work place and she has been living with her. But she lives the three-year-old with her husband who is unemployed. Today I noticed the child in a limpy walking style or like a woman who just gave birth and had some stitches down &#039;there’. Since am a mother myself I carried the child and after some questions she told me Ati daddy alinipaka mafuta huku chini alafu akaniweka dudu kubwa! Pliz I need any child rescue number saa hizi,” &lt;/em&gt;the post reads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That one post snowballed from a handful of responses to an 800 member-strong Facebook page campaign totally dedicated to the rescue and safety of the child including raising funds for food and clothing as well as following up her case with the police. It was one of these members who suggested that the child be taken to Doctors Without Borders or MSF in Mathare. Doctors at MSF confirmed that the child had been defiled. Eric, who personally worked with the couple and lived close to them in Kayole, says the process has been excruciatingly slow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We had to report the matter to the Kayole Police station, even though we had been at the District Office just a day before. The DO said they could not handle it despite the fact that they have a Children&#039;s Department. For the child’s safety she was taken to the Imani Children’s Centre by the Police. But it has taken very long for them to act. It took almost three weeks for us to get the P3 form and this was only after telling them that Jane&#039;s case was a hot story in the news. They are also yet to move in and question the woman that the baby was staying with. But finally Cradle (the children&#039;s foundation) has stepped in and has taken up her case,” Eric says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lady who rescued Baby Jane speaks bitterly of her experience: “My husband and I followed up with the police and child welfare services but nothing was done. They kept asking for money for investigations to begin yet we were not even the guardians or the parents of the child. We became frustrated so I decided to stop following up the issue,” she says. “Anyway I think nothing else can be done for the child. We went to MSF a second time and the doctors found that she had not been infected with any Sexually Transmitted Infections (STI’s) and she is in a safe place so she is fine. ”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community workers Mercy Ahoya, Emily Kwamboka and Susan say Baby Jane should count herself as one of the lucky few who actually get a P3. As community workers from Kibra and Mathare slums respectively, they say experience has shown them that getting a P3 for victims of sexual assault, especially poor victims, is next to impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To get a P3 you have to wake up very early. You should be at the police station by 4am or 5am. If you go at 11am, they will tell you it is not there. It is very hard to get a P3. Even having woken up that early it is very difficult. I do not know why it has to be this hard,” says Mercy who works for the Harmlet, a Kibra-based NGO that helps rehabilitate young survivors of sexual violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, she is following up a case that has already taken months yet the conclusion seems nowhere in sight. “The police have asked for money, which the girl’s mother does not have. They keep telling us to come back another day. They have also told us that according to them the victim is a big girl, so there may have been no rape and whatever happened was consensual,” Mercy says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She adds that most victim or their relatives get nowhere without help. She says the P3 form will only materialise if they have the backing of large NGOs. “And the victim should go with one of the people who work in these organisations,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise insults or demands for kitu kidogo (bribe) will pause as unmovable stumbling blocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most guardians or parents give up and console themselves with the fact that at least the victim has gotten medication to prevent STI’s or pregnancy and has gone through counseling,” Mercy adds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two rape victims Esther and Jane (not their real names) say their cases never went anywhere because of these impediments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know what the policeman said to my aunt, but she got angry and we left. I think he insulted her.” Esther says of the time her aunt had tried to report the matter of her husband sexually abusing her niece to the police in Kibra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Esther’s uncle raped her repeatedly while she was living with him and her aunt after the death of her parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I had to stay alone with him when my aunt was at work and I wasn’t going to school,” she recalls. “He would force me to sleep with him and threatened to kill both me and my aunt if I told her what was happening.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane also tells her story. “It was in 2011. I was 12 when my auntie&#039;s boyfriend started raping me. When another aunt, my father’s sister, came to visit, I told her and we went to the police. This was in Kawangware. He asked for money, but my aunt did not have any so we left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She says the aunt who rescued her and reported the matter also took her to a hospital where doctors discovered she was four months pregnant as a result of the rape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She took me to another hospital in Dagoretti where they gave me some pills. My stomach started hurting really badly after I took them. I complained to my aunt and she said it was supposed to hurt as I was having an abortion,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One community worker who works with sexual assault victims in Mathare says the situation is not different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mathare police officers will only agree to fill P3 forms if the victim has a medical report or post rape care (PRC) form from either the Nairobi Women’s Hospital or MSF. PRC forms from other clinics do not seem to count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a community worker, Susan has also witnessed victims deal with such questions or statements as “you were an adult so how can you be raped? You must have enjoyed it”. She says policemen in charge of the stations at night are usually the harshest stating that one common excuse they give is that the government has not provided the police with enough fuel to search for rapists. Emily, who is also a community worker in Mathare, says even after being issued the P3 the process that follows is still tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She says after the form is filled at the police station the victim still has to go to the police surgeon in Nairobi, another torturous task as the doctor serves assault victims from as far as Kiambu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have to be at the police surgeon’s door by 5am. People practically live inside that compound just to see the doctor. But the queue is so long that you may be turned away before he even sees you,” Emily says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She adds that the situation is worsened by the fact that the doctor is a man examining both male and female victims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily says the relationship between police officers and people within the slums need to change. She says there is no bond between the officers and the people they are meant to protect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We give them nicknames like Sanse and Karau because we do fear them,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teresa Omondi-Adeitan, deputy executive director at the Federation of Women Lawyers (FIDA) agrees with the community workers that the P3 can be hard to obtain. “ Yes we have seen this a lot of times. There are times when the form is honestly not there and victims and even their advocates are told to come back another day,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theresa also  emphasises that victims should have the support of an organised group when reporting the crime whether an NGO, faith best or even community self help group. She says that after a lot of lobbying from NGOs the form that would have come at a cost of Sh150 or Sh50 is now free and even downloadable on the internet, but it is still unreachable for women in rural areas and slum who do not have access to such facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is also a matter of being a bit more aggressive. If the police officer is not there, ask to speak to the officer in charge of the station or the next in command. Sometimes the police officer just wants a bribe, why else would the form only materialise when an official from NGO is there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She however stresses that it is not only the police surgeon in Nairobi who can fill the report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is no ‘daktari wa P3’. A P3 can be filled by any government doctor or clinical officer. But I understand why they perceive it as such. Many government doctors do not like filling the P3 because it means going to court and being a witness. That’s why in most communities most people go to doctor so and so because they know he will fill the form and come to court no matter how many times the case is adjourned. An internal arrangement is then formed were the police will refer survivors to this one doctor because they know he is co-operative and no warrants will have to be issued to force him to come to court. Police surgeon Dr Zephaniah Kamau in Nairobi is one of these doctors,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She explains that this “internal arrangement” is relied upon so heavily by victims and the police because if the doctor does not show up the case will be lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If it is adjourned again and again because of the doctor’s absence then the magistrate gets annoyed at the prosecutor and tells him or her that the doctor must come because without the doctors evidence the case is going nowhere. In fact for defilement cases, without medical evidence you do not have a case.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The line at the police surgeon’s office housed within the traffic police headquarters adjacent to the Kenyatta National Hospital is just as Emily described. It has three phases. Phase one is for the lucky few seated on plastic chairs in a waiting room inside the building. Those in phase two form a line that begins from inside the waiting room and snakes passed the door right outside the building. Then those in phase three lie littered on the grass compound outside under the punishing sun, exhausted by the hours of waiting. The receptionist says that Dr Kamau is not in because he is himself unwell and in hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another doctor is standing in for him but cannot be interviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peris, who has come to have her report filled, estimates that she might be number 65. She looks up of from her position on the grass with a red blot on the whites of her right eye and bruises circling both eyes. She has been waiting to see the doctor since 6.30 am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is almost 2pm and Peris and the friend who has accompanied her cannot leave for lunch because they will most likely be pushed further down the line. She says her boyfriend bruised her because she refused to let him back into her life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I refused he beat me up and took my child,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She is hoping to see the doctor today and finally begin court proceedings against her ex-boyfriend and get back her child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do not know if it will happen,” she says. “Since morning only 15 of us have been served. It’s like there is some bribery going on because there are people coming in with big cars and they are being served ahead of us and their things are being sorted out faster.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCPD at the Kilimani Police Station Peter Katam says that all police stations should ideally have a Gender Violence and Children’s desk whose officers are trained to deal with Sexual Gender Based Violence cases with the sensitivity they deserve. However, he says some officers may not be trained in these area and urges community based organisations to help train the officers on how to deal with these cases and the rest of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corrine Torre, project co-ordinator for MSF in Mathare and Eastleigh, agrees that there should be more training of police officers. However, she says despite the negative reputation that surrounds the police, they really helped in helping to curb violence cases in areas such as Mathare and Kibera. “Over 50 per cent of cases referred to MSF clinics are by the Police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MSF has managed to cultivate a good relationship with the police over the years. They have been a really great help to us in trying to help survivors.” She adds that one difficulty that both the police and medical centres such as MSF face is the growing number of violence cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We deal with 130 to 150 cases per month in Mathare alone. We began to see an increase when we opened the clinic for 24 hours seven days a week.” Corrine says she expects this number to grow as MSF heightens its campaign to sensitise the communities about sexual violence victims MSF’s toll free helpline 0711400506.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teresa Omondi-Adeitan says the system should be improved quickly or Kenya risks creating a bitter society that may implode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In addition to the rape, victims also become bitter with the system. In some cases we also have children who grow up to be rapists because they were raped themselves. So are we creating more rapists? We need to create a healing society by ensuring that victims feel justice has truly been done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>12/18/2013 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY LYDIA MATATA</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-147725/rape-and-elusive-p3-form&quot;&gt;Rape And The Elusive P3 Form&lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-141996/emergency-contraception-top-five-facts&quot;&gt;Emergency contraception: Top five facts &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/features%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EFeatures%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;!--  P { margin-bottom: 0.08in; direction: ltr; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); widows: 2; orphans: 2; }A:link { color: rgb(0, 0, 255); }  --&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Whether the condom slipped your mind or off the penis, it&#039;s usually followed by some frantic calculations (&#039;Could I be fertile right now?&#039;) and a rush to the pharmacy in search of a ‘morning-after pill’. But there are many options, so don&#039;t panic…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) E-pill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergency pill, or e-pill, is available over the counter at pharmacies in Kenya so you don’t need a doctor&#039;s prescription. The e-pill is very effective in preventing &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/pregnancy&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pregnancies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; after unprotected sex, if you take it as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some brands, you take one pill; with others, you will have to take two, 12-hours apart. Check with the pharmacist or a healthcare professional for the right instructions. Some women have side-effects like nausea and vomiting when they take the e-pill. Also, it could have an effect on the timing of your next period. And remember: the “e” stands for emergency – the e-pill should not be used as a normal contraception method.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) When to take the e-pill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The e-pill is most effective if it&#039;s taken as soon as possible after you had &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/safe-or-unsafe&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;unprotected sex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; . Many health care providers even suggested getting an emergency pill and keeping it at home just in case.&lt;br /&gt;However the e-pill can still be effective if you take it 72 hours after sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) &lt;strong&gt;Is the e-pill an abortion pill?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. The e-pill is not an &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/tags/abortion-pill&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;abortion pill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The e-pill works in various ways, but can&#039;t do anything if an egg is already fertilized. If you take the e-pill before ovulation, the e-pill tricks your body into thinking that ovulation has already happened, so it delays ovulation. It also thickens the mucus on your cervix, making it hard for sperm to get into the womb. That way it stops you from getting pregnant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you already are pregnant and take the e-pill, it will have no negative effects on your pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4) &lt;strong&gt;IUDs as emergency contraception&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another very effective method of emergency contraception is fitting a Copper-T &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/term/iud-copper&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IUD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, also known as the ‘coil’. Actually, it&#039;s the most effective form of emergency contraception. You need to see a doctor though to have it put in place, and it can be a bit pricey. The Copper-T (Paragard) has one potential additional advantage: it can stay in a woman&#039;s body for up to 10 years afterwards as a normal and super-effective birth control method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5) &lt;strong&gt;The Yuzpe-method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also take some brands of combined oral contraceptives (&#039;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/pill&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the pill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#039;) in higher doses. This is called the Yuzpe-method. But because the side-effects are high and it&#039;s not very effective, you should look into other methods rather than this one. Even taking higher doses of progestogen-only pills (&#039;the &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/term/mini-pill&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mini-pill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&#039;) is more effective than the Yuzpe-method, but can also have lots of side-effects. So you should talk to a healthcare provider before using either method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More resources on: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/emergency-contraception&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emergency contraception&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read more about: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/news/e-pill-was-my-life-saver&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The e-pill was my life-saver!”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More articles on: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/tags/emergency-contraception&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;emergency contraception&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;, &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/tags/birth-control&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;birth control&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;, &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/tags/unplanned-pregnancy&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;unplanned pregnancy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>10/26/2013 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY STEPHANIE HAASE</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-141996/emergency-contraception-top-five-facts&quot;&gt;Emergency contraception: Top five facts &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-137156/what-tell-your-kids-about-sex&quot;&gt;What to tell your kids about sex &lt;/a&gt;</title>
    <link>http://www.the-star.co.ke/%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/features%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EFeatures%3C/a%3E%2C%20%3Ca%20href%3D%22/tags/star-health%22%20typeof%3D%22skos%3AConcept%22%20property%3D%22rdfs%3Alabel%20skos%3AprefLabel%22%3EStar%20Health%3C/a%3E</link>
    <description>&lt;!--  P { margin-bottom: 0.08in; direction: ltr; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); widows: 2; orphans: 2; }A:link { color: rgb(0, 0, 255); }  --&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As parents we like to think that our children remain babies until they walk into their own homes. But it’s now time to acknowledge that our offspring grow up…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If are children are not only to survive but to also thrive in society, you need to equip them with knowledge on the facts of life. The first fact will be to acknowledge human beings have sex not just for reproduction but for pleasure as well. Once you admit this, then you shall find it necessary to also include some more facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/condoms-0&quot;&gt;Condoms&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Let your child know that there is no better protection than using a condom; and no matter how much the guy claims to love her, condom use should not be negotiable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/term/abstinence&quot;&gt;Abstinence&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Of course you would want your child to wait until she’s older but it’s their body and therefore their choice. Just let them know that it’s not a choice to be made because everyone else has made their “sexual debut”. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/birth-control-methods&quot;&gt;Contraceptives&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; If your child chooses to have sex, you don’t want her life interrupted because of a “slip-up”. She might need to get on a more long-term contraceptive method and you would want her to have the best. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/term/abortion&quot;&gt;Pregnancy and abortion&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Even with the best protection, one can still become pregnant. You might want to let your child know “it’s not the end of the world”. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/term/first-time-sex&quot;&gt;First time&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;/strong&gt;Yes you can get pregnant the first time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First person:&lt;/strong&gt; Not just the first person who tells you I &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/love&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; you.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OB/GYN:&lt;/strong&gt; Once your child attains &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/puberty&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sexual maturity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; it’s important to always follow-up on her sexual health. &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/hiv&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HIV&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/tags/std&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;s tests should be addressed for both males and females. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk:&lt;/strong&gt; Let your child know that they not only can talk to you. In fact they should never be afraid to speak up, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/talking-about-sex&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;even with their own partners&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The bottom line should be that they are comfortable with themselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More resources on: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/resource/talking-about-sex&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talking about sex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read more about: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/news/first-time-sex-top-five-facts&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First time sex: top five facts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt; and &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/news/talking-about-sex-dos-and-donts&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talking about sex: do’s and don&#039;ts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More articles on: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/tags/sex-education&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sex education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt; and &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lovematters.co.ke/tags/safe-sex&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;safe sex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>09/14/2013 - 00:00</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BY DIANA ESTHER WANGARI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">&lt;a href=&quot;/news/article-137156/what-tell-your-kids-about-sex&quot;&gt;What to tell your kids about sex &lt;/a&gt;</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
